Guide to the Antonio Ochoa Carrillo Papers and Benito Juárez Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Antonio Ochoa Carrillo papers and Benito Juárez correspondence
1852-1871
1864-1866
WA MSS S-2938
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(1 box) + 1 broadside folder
The papers of Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1852-1871, with letters that provide extensive information about the European Intervention in Mexico and limited documentation related to the Reform War in Mexico. Includes 56 letters from Mexican president Benito Juárez, as well as 12 letters from others, including future Mexican presidents Sebastián Lerdo de Tejada and José María Iglesias, as well as Mexican General Ramón Corona. The collection also includes five draft letters written by Ochoa.
Ochoa Carrillo, Antonio, 1811-1883
Juárez, Benito, 1806-1872
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Formerly owned by James S. Copley. Purchased from William Reese Co. on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2013.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Antonio Ochoa Carrillo (1811-1883)
Antonio Ochoa Carrillo (1811-1883) was a Mexican attorney and mine owner, who served as governor of Chihuahua from 1857 to 1861 and 1873 to 1877. Born in Culiacán, Sinaloa, Ochoa received a law degree in Guadalajara in 1839. He operated mines in Chihuahua in the Guadalupe y Calvo mining district. As governor of Chihuahua, Ochoa endorsed liberal reforms, including compulsory education for children, as well as established a state lottery to support local charities.
Benito Juárez (1806-1872)
Benito Juárez (born Benito Pablo Juárez García) was a Mexican lawyer and politician of Zapotec origin from Oaxaca. He served five terms as president of Mexico (1858-1872), as well as Governor of Oaxaca, 1847-1852. He was the first Mexican leader who did not have a military background, the first full-blooded indigenous national ever to serve as President of Mexico and to lead a country in the Western Hemisphere. During his terms as president, the government led by Juárez resisted the French occupation, overthrew the Mexican Empire, and restored the Republic of Mexico. His administrations also used liberal efforts to modernize the country.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1852-1871, with letters that provide extensive information about the European Intervention in Mexico and limited documentation related to the Reform War in Mexico. Includes 56 letters from Mexican president Benito Juárez, as well as 12 letters from others, including future Mexican presidents Sebastián Lerdo de Tejada and José María Iglesias, as well as Mexican General Ramón Corona. The collection also includes five draft letters written by Ochoa.
Letters by Juárez offer accounts of the political, military, and financial conflicts, from the flight of the government into exile in 1863 through the defeat of Maximilian and the Mexican Empire in 1867. They document his part of a weekly correspondence with Ochoa Carrillo, sharing news of troop movements, battles, political maneuvers, and foreign diplomacy.
Printed material includes three printed circulars published in July-August 1859 by Manuel F. Ruiz, the Minister of Justice for Ecclesiastical Affairs and Public Instruction, Santos Degollado, Commander in Chief of the Federal Army; and Melchor Ocampo, Minister of the Interior, as well as a supplement of the Del Siglo XIX newspaper, which prints a letter from Juarez to the citizens of Mexico after the invasion by the French Army.
Most letters are accompanied by typescripts created by a former unidentified owner of the Spanish text, as well as English translations. However, many of these contain transcription and translation errors.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Mexico -- History -- 1821-1861; Mexico -- History -- 1867-1910; Mexico -- History -- European intervention, 1861-1867; Corona, Ramón, 1837-1889; Degollado, Santos, 1811-1861; Iglesias, José María, 1823-1891; Juárez, Benito, 1806-1872; Lerdo de Tejada, Sebastián, 1823-1889; Maximilian, Emperor of Mexico, 1832-1867; Ocampo, Melchor, 1814-1861; Ochoa Carrillo, Antonio, 1811-1883; Ruiz, Manuel F.; Mexico. Ejército Federal; Mexico. Ministerio de Justicia y Negocios Eclesiásticos; Mexico. Secretaría de Gobernación; Copley, James S. (James Strohn) -- Ownership
- Papers and Correspondence, 1852-1871; 0.42; (1 box) + 1 broadside folder
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence chiefly to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, as well as some letters written by him and printed material.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Oaxaca, to Bonifacio Gutierres, M. Payno, and Tore Joaquin Pesado, 1852 July 29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    As governor of Oaxaca, Juárez discusses the work of the committee on public credit.
    Accompanied by an English translation typescript.
  - Ruiz, Manuel F., Ministerio de Justicia, Negocios Eclesiásticos e Instrucción Pública. Printed circular. Veracruz, 1859 July 12 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    In this circular, Ruiz discusses limiting the secular role of clergy.
  - Degollado, Santos, General en Jefe, Mexico Ejército Federal. Printed circular. Tampico de Tamaulipas, 1859 July 18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    In this circular, Degollado (born José Santos Degollado Sánchez) commends Juárez and other secretaries for their work against the partisans of the clergy.
  - Ocampo, Melchor, Secretaría de Estado y del Despacho de Gobernación. Printed circular. Veracruz, 1859 August 6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Circular on the secular role of the clergy.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Mexico, to Mariano Degollado in Washington, D.C, 1861 February 26 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Juárez thanks Degollado for his enthusiastic response to the Liberal victory at the Battle of Calpulalpan during the War of Reform.
  - Supplement Number 453, Del Siglo XIX. Mexico City, Mexico, 1862 April 2 (Box 2 (Broadside))
    Newspaper supplement of the Del Siglo XIX, published by Ignacio Cumplido, which prints a letter from Benito Juárez to the citizens of Mexico. He explains that Great Britain, France, and Spain have broken negotiations, and urges Mexicans to defend the independence of their country in the wake of the invasion by the French Army.
  - Ochoa Carrillo, Antonio. Autograph letter, signed: Guadalupe y Calvo, Chihuahua, to Benito Juárez, 1864 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Ochoa expresses his pleasure that Juárez established the government-in-exile in Chihuahua. He also reports his expectation to raise 1,500 to 2,000 men for the war. He also mentions the anarchy in Sinaloa
    Accompanied by a transcription and English translation typescripts.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Hidalgo del Parral, Chihuahua, to Jésus Rios y Valles, 1864 October 5 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Juárez discusses increased morale in Chihuahua after he established the government-in-exile.
    The letter includes a secretarial transcription and interlinear French translation.
    Accompanied by an English translation and historical background typescripts.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to General Gaspar Sánchez Ochoa, 1864 November 24 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Benito urgently reports the arrival of French troops at Río Florido, which makes communication unsafe.
    Accompanied by a transcription and English translation typescripts, as well as a photocopy of a typescript description of the letter.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1864 December 24 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Juárez describes Mexican troop movements in Culiacán and French troop movements in Durango.
  - Ochoa Carrillo, Antonio. Autograph letter: Guadalupe y Calvo, Chihuahua, to Benito Juárez, 1865 January 20 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Ochoa considers rewards for victorious Mexican military officers, and expresses his pleasure with the French defeat in Oaxaca.
    Accompanied by a transcription and English translation transcripts.
  - Lerdo de Tejada y Corral, Sebastián. Secretarial letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 January 24 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Lerdo de Tejada (born Sebastián Lerdo de Tejada y Corral) thanks Ochoa for forwarded military dispatches.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 January 24 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Juárez thanks Ochoa for military dispatches sent to General José María Patoni. He also describes the arrival of French prisoners of war at Álamos, Sonora, as well as reports French troops advancing on Chihuahua. Juárez also seeks news from Sinaloa.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 February 7 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Juárez writes that he approves of execution of prisoners of war by General Ramón Corona (born Ramón Corona Madrigal) as reprisal for the execution of Mexican prisoners of war. He also orders Colonel Remedios Meza to leave for Tamazula de Victoria in Durango, or lose his command. Juárez also reports a mutiny by soldiers commanded by General José María Jesús Carbajal.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 February 21 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Juárez discusses infighting among military commanders, specifically between General José María Patoni and General Antonio Rosales, including threats by the latter to defect.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 March 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Juárez reports that General Antonio Rosales plans to hand over his command in Sinaloa to General Gaspar Sánchez Ochoa, and asks Ochoa to negotiate the transfer. He also reports that Colonel Remedios Meza arrived in Tamazula de Victoria and General José María Jesús Carbajal planned a return to Durango.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 March 14 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Juárez reports that General Antonio Rosales sent Esteban Guiccione to report on actions in Sinaloa. He continues by expressing his frustration over the affair. Juárez also reports the enemy pursuing the force commanded by Colonel Remedios Meza in Tamazula de Victoria.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Juárez expresses gratitude to Ochoa for negotiating with General Antonio Rosales, and his hopes for a rapid resolution. He also reports on military movements in Coahuila, Durango, and Zacatecas.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 March 25 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Juárez reports that General Antonio Rosales handed over his command in Sinaloa to General Gaspar Sánchez Ochoa. He also reports that the government can only provide General Ochoa half of the six thousand pesos he requested due to limited treasury funds following expenditures for the expedition into Durango.
  - Iglesias, José María. Autograph letter, signed: Guadalupe y Calvo, Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 March 25 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    In his role as the Minister of Finance, Iglesias (born José María Iglesias Inzaurraga) states that duties on foreign products in Chihuahua would more than provide the three thousand pesos General Gaspar Sánchez Ochoa requested from the government. He also directs Ochoa to remit extra funds to him.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 March 27 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Juárez report that he sent General Antonio Rosales his formal appointment following the transfer of his command to General Gaspar Sánchez Ochoa. He also reiterates that General Ochoa should only receive three thousand pesos. Juárez concludes with brief reports of troop movements in Coahuila, including forces commanded by General Mariano Antonio Guadalupe Escobedo de la Peña.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 April 4 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Juárez expresses gratitude to Ochoa for negotiating with General Antonio Rosales. He also reports on troop movements in Durango and Coahuila. Juárez celebrates the decision by the United States government not to recognize Ferdinand Maximilian as Maximilian I, Emperor of Mexico. He concludes by asking Ochoa to supply additional troops from Chihuahua to support the offensive in Durango, as well as publishing a newspaper to support the government-in-exile.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 April 11 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Juárez reports on troop movements in Coahuila, Durango, and Nuevo León.
  - Iglesias, José María. Autograph letter, signed: Guadalupe y Calvo, Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Iglesias approves an increase in a disbursement of 4,800 pesos to General Gaspar Sánchez Ochoa based on justifications given by Antonio Ochoa. He also states that the Mexican treasury will levy 2,500 pesos against the Morelos Municipality in Chihuahua, as well as duties on silver production.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Juárez approves of the manner that Ochoa distributed monies to General Gaspar Sánchez Ochoa. He reports that French forces commanded by Armand Alexandre de Castagny occupy the port of Guaymas, Sonora without resistance, and that he plans on sending a force commanded by General Pedro Meoqui Mañón to Parral, Chihuahua.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 April 25 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Custodial History
    Juárez reports on troop movements in Coahuila and Nuevo León. He expresses his disappointment that some Mexicans citizens side with the foreign enemies rather than stand with their fellow citizens. Juarez states that he has warned General José María Jesús Carbajal to control looting by his soldiers in Chihuahua. He also mentions the execution of Caballero, a spy for the French.
  - Iglesias, José María. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Based on a recommendation by Ochoa, Iglesias reports that he exempted Cipriano Peña from studies and an examination to qualify as a barrister.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Juárez expresses doubt that foreign troops will attack Chihuahua. He also reports on troop movements in Coahuila. Nuevo León, and Tamaulipas as well as the surrender of Robert E. Lee and assassination of Abraham Lincoln.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Juárez reports that the French have not invaded Culiacán, Sinaloa, and that they appear dismayed by the recent defeat of the Confederate States of America.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Juárez discusses the lack of currency in the Mexican Treasury to purchase gunpowder. He relays reports from General Antonio Rosales that reinforcements may come from the United States. Juárez closes with news that troops commanded by General Miguel Negrete Novoa returned to Monterrey, Nuevo León, to prepare for a movement into Luis Potosí.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 May 26 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Juárez reports of a mutiny in Culiacán, Sinaloa, as well as the likelihood that French troops were marching on Monterrey, Nuevo León, or they were marching on the states of Durango and Zacatecas. He also reports that French General François Achille Bazaine has ordered the 1st Regiment of the Zouaves to march on Mexico City.
    Accompanied by a transcription.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 May 30 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Juárez expresses his pleasure to Ochoa's report of the quelled mutiny against General Antonio Rosales in Culiacán. He continues that they should give amnesty to Ascensión Correa and other mutineers. Juárez reports that French troops were marching on Monterrey, Nuevo León.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Juárez briefly expresses his pleasure to news that General Antonio Rosales controls Sinaloa.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Juárez refers to terms for Ochoa to purchase gunpowder. He also mentions the dismissal of General Antonio Rosales, as well as troop movements in Coahuila, including General Miguel Negrete Novoa in Saltillo and French troops under the command of General Agustín Enrique Brincourt in Parras.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 June 20 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Juárez reports communication with General Meza that he planned to take Santiago Papasquiaro, Durango, with General Ramón Corona, which conflicts with a recent report from Ochoa that Corona marched on Mazatlán. He consequently awaits further communication from the generals, as well as news from troop movements in Coahuila. Juárez also reports that troops under General Ignacio Pesqueira García occupy Hermosillo, Sonora.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 June 23 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Juárez reports that a planned attack on Santiago Papasquiaro, Durango, did not occur because the forces did not arrive.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 July 4 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Juárez mentions the resignation of Antonio Rosales as the governor of Sinaloa and the appointment of Domingo Rubí. He also reports troop movements in Durango, Sinaloa, and San Luis Potosí.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 July 11 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Juárez comments at length on the resignation of Antonio Rosales as the governor of Sinaloa and the appointment of Domingo Rubí, but state that he will reserve judgment until he receive more information. He also reports troop movements in Durango and Chihuahua.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 July 21 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Juárez responds to a report from Ochoa that General Ramón Corona acquired funds and supplies from the Cantón de Mina in Chihuahua, contrary to a tardy order from Juárez. He also reports on the movement of troops under the command of General Miguel Negrete from Durango arrival in Chihuahua. Juárez expresses doubt that the French will attack Chihuahua. He also adds a postscript reporting the resignation of Negrete.
  - Azcárate, Juan Francisco. Autograph letter, signed: Guadalupe y Calvo, Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 July 23 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Azcárate transmits a request from General Ramón Corona for Ochoa to represent his interests.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 August 4 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Juárez reiterates that General Ramón Corona not supplies from the Cantón de Mina in Chihuahua. He reports the arrival of the French are in Chihuahua, and their imminent occupation of the city of Chihuahua. He blames the retreat of General Miguel Negrete from Durango to Chihuahua for the attack. Nevertheless, Juárez expresses confidence that troop movements in the interior states will prove victorious. He closes by stating he will relocate to El Paso del Norte, and leave General Manuel Ojinaga in command of Chihuahua.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Villa del Paso, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Juárez expresses his confidence that the united Republican forces will cause the Empire to yield or retreat. He also states that after the imminent departure of the invaders from Chihuahua, he will probably return to Chihuahua City.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Villa del Paso, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Juárez reports that the French have left Chihuahua City, and that plans to return. He also ordered General José María Patoni should march on Durango and harass the retreating troops under the command of General François Achille Bazaine. He closes with his appointment of Luis Terrazas as military commander and governor of Chihuahua.
  - Juárez, Benito. Secretarial autograph, signed letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 November 23 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Juárez reports the return of the government to Chihuahua City, and refers to non-extant enclosures.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: Chihuahua, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1865 November 28 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Juárez briefly reports that French troops en route to Chihuahua, and asks Ochoa to warn Domingo Rubí and General Ramón Corona about the advancing French troops in Sinaloa.
  - d'Albicy, Count. Letter signed: Parral, to Antonio Ochoa, 1866 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Lieutenant Colonel Count d'Albicy asks Ochoa to intercede for peace in Guadalupe y Calvo and recognize the Mexican Empire.
  - Ochoa Carrillo, Antonio. Autograph draft letter, signed: Guadalupe y Calvo, to Count d'Abicy, 1866 January (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Ochoa politely refuses to recognize the legitimacy of the Mexican Empire.
  - Ochoa Carrillo, Antonio. Autograph draft letter: Guadalupe y Calvo, to Count d'Abicy, 1866 January (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Ochoa identifies himself as the Captaincy General of the Tarahumara (also known as the Rarámuri), and admantly refuses to recognize the legitimacy of the Mexican Empire.
  - Domínguez, Joaquín H. Autograph letter, signed: Hidalgo, to Antonio Ochoa, 1866 January 9 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Dominguiz reports that the Mexican Empire has created the department of Batopilas with him at its head.
  - Ochoa Carrillo, Antonio. Autograph draft letter: Guadalupe y Calvo, to General Ramón Corona, 1866 January 20 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Draft letters on a single leaf.
    In his letter to Dominguez, Ochoa refuses to support the recognition of the department of Batopilas.
    In his letter to Corona, Ochoa introduces his friend Ángel D. Martínez of Culiacán and a partial owner of mines at San José de las Bocas.
    Accompanied by transcriptions and English translation typescripts
  - Ochoa Carrillo, Antonio. Autograph letter, signed: Guadalupe y Calvo, to Ramón Corona, 1866 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Ochoa congratulates Corona on his military victories and belittles the ambitions of Napoleon III.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: El Paso del Norte, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1866 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Juárez briefly reports progress by the Republic in Coahuila, Nuevo León, and Tamaulipas, as well as Morelia in Michoacán. He includes clippings (non-extant) related to a decree made by Juárez on November 8, 1865, that General Jesús González Ortega was in dereliction of his duties after abandoning his troops and Mexico.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: El Paso del Norte, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1866 May 26 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    Juárez briefly reports he will shortly return to Chihuahua City.
  - Juárez, Benito. Autograph letter, signed: El Paso del Norte, to Antonio Ochoa Carrillo, 1866 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 53)